Finding Aid for Jennifer Granholm papers, 1992-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jennifer Granholm papers 1992-2010 2003-2010
Granholm, Jennifer.
2011101 Aa 2
Granholm was the Democratic governor of Michigan from 2003 to 2010. Records are primarily arranged by office of origin and staff member and document Granholm's service as governor. The series in the collection are: Transition 2002, Legal Division, Policy Division, Executive Office, Communications Division, Economic Recovery Office, Northern Michigan Office, Other Executive Divisions, Office of the Lieutenant Governor, Office of the First Gentleman, Archived Websites, and Memorabilia. The collection includes paper and electronic files and audio-visual materials. Extensively documented topics include economic diversification, renewable energy, environmental issues, education, Michigan's response to the 2008 financial crisis, the Governor's Hearing on the Removal of Kwame Kilpatrick from the office of Mayor of Detroit, and Michigan soldiers killed in Iraq and Afghanistan.
225 linear feet in 227 boxes
1 oversize folders
7 oversize items
233.9 GB
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Jennifer Granholm (donor no. 10483 ) in 2011.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
Portions of The Granholm papers are restricted in accordance with the terms of the donation agreement.
The following series, or parts of series, will remain closed to research until January 1, 2018:
Legal Division -- Boxes 2 – 123 and digital files
Executive Division -- Boxes 148 – 169 and digital files
Office of the Lt. Governor -- Boxes 213 – 216 and files
Office of the First Gentleman -- Boxes 179, 217 – 222, and digital files
Jennifer Granholm was born February 5, 1959 in Vancouver, British Columbia to Shirley Alfreda Dowden and Victor Ivar Granholm. At the age of four, Granholm's family moved to California; she grew up in Anaheim, San Jose, and San Carlos. Granholm earned a B.A. in Political Science from the University of California at Berkeley in 1984 and continued her education at Harvard Law School. After receiving her J.D. in 1987, Granholm moved to Michigan where she began her career as a law clerk for Judge Damon Keith of the U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals. In 1990 she became a U. S. Prosecutor in Detroit, and served as corporation counsel for Wayne County from 1994 to 1996 before becoming the general counsel for the Detroit and Wayne County Stadium Authority.
Granholm entered statewide politics in 1998 when she ran for Attorney General on the Democratic ticket. She was the only Democrat elected to statewide office that year and served in the position through 2002. Towards the end of her term she had gained enough statewide recognition to enter the governor's race. Announcing her candidacy in March of 2001, she defeated both former governor James Blanchard and House Democratic Whip David Bonior to win the Democratic primary. In November of 2002, she won the general election, defeating Republican Lieutenant Governor Dick Posthumus to become Michigan's first female governor.
Granholm took office as Michigan's 47th governor on January 1, 2003. The beginning of her tenure as governor coincided with a difficult period in Michigan's economic history. As the rest of the country recovered from the 2001 recession, Michigan continued to struggle. In her first year as governor, Granholm faced a $3 billion budget deficit and a rising unemployment rate. Her administration's response to the challenges it faced reflected Granholm's moderate approach by focusing on reinforcing education, promoting economic diversification, and improving government efficiency through cost cutting and streamlining.
Despite challenges early in her first term, Granholm set about an extensive program of cuts to state expenditures in order to balance Michigan's budget. She continued to seek cost saving measures throughout her first term. Granholm also focused on education and, in 2004, established the Cherry Commission, headed by Lieutenant Governor John Cherry, to study ways to double the number of college graduates in Michigan. She also implemented rigorous K-8 standards through the State Board of Education, increased high school graduation requirements, and created the Early Childhood Investment Corporation.
After two years in office, as Michigan's economy began to stall, Granholm pursued a multi-pronged effort to spur job creation and increase the state's flagging tax base. In 2005, Granholm kicked off her economic revitalization program with the 21st Century Jobs Fund, a $2 billion program that used tobacco settlement funds to encourage diversification in the state's economy. Granholm also launched the Pure Michigan advertising campaign to promote tourism and Michigan's leisure industry. The administration viewed Google's choice of Ann Arbor for its AdWords operation as a victory for its diversification efforts. In addition to pursuing economic diversification, Granholm created the Michigan Earned Income Tax Credit and signed bills that increased the minimum wage.
With the continued downward spiral of Michigan's economy, including the loss of Greenville, Michigan's Electrolux plant to Juarez, Mexico in 2004, Granholm faced a tough re-election bid in 2006. Despite a concerted challenge from Republican Dick DeVos, a concerted campaign effort from early September through Election Day led to Granholm's eventual re-election.
Granholm's second term focused primarily on Michigan's economy. She launched the term with No Worker Left Behind, a program designed to give unemployed and under-employed workers the opportunity to receive training for high-demand jobs. The governor's other efforts at job creation included emphasizing the clean and renewable energy industry and incentives for the production of auto batteries. In April, 2008, Granholm announced a set of film incentives. The incentive package was designed to both create jobs immediately and spur long-term growth. After the financial crisis of 2008, Granholm redoubled her efforts on behalf of Michigan's economy, speaking out on behalf of the state's beleaguered auto industry during the federal bailout and pursuing increased efforts at diversification. In addition to her work on behalf of Michigan's economy, Granholm also signed the Promise Zone legislation in 2008 to give students in high-poverty communities the opportunity to attend college, presided over the hearing regarding the removal of Detroit Mayor Kwame Kilpatrick, and reorganized and shut down several state departments in the interest of increased efficiency and budgetary restraint.
Granholm is currently Distinguished Practitioner of Law and Public Policy at her alma mater, the University of California at Berkeley, serves on the Board of Trustees of the Dow Chemical Corporation, and is a Senior Advisor to the Pew Charitable Trusts' Clean Energy Program. She married Daniel Mulhern in 1986 and they have three children.
Summary Contents List
Transition 2002 -- Box 1
Legal Division -- Boxes 2 -- 123, Outsize, and Online
Policy Division -- Boxes 124 -- 147 and Online
Executive Division -- Boxes 148 -- 169 and Online
Communications Division -- Boxes 170 -- 196 and Online
Economic Recovery Office -- Boxes 197 -- 199 and Online
Northern Michigan Office -- Boxes 200 -- 205 and Online
Other Executive Divisions -- Boxes 205 -- 212 and Online
Office of the Lt. Governor -- Boxes 213 -- 216 and Online
Office of the First Gentleman -- Boxes 179, 217 -- 222, and Online
Archived Websites -- Online
Memorabilia -- Boxes 223 -- 227 and Outsize
The Jennifer Granholm collection consists of paper records, analog audio-visual material (photographs, audio and video recordings), and digital files (word processing documents, spreadsheets, .PDF files, image files, digital audio and video files, and archived web pages). The digital files were received on hard drives, DVDs and other media, and through website capture. All digital files have been transferred to the University of Michigan servers and in some cases reformatted according to accepted preservation standards. The original file structure has been maintained to the extent possible and is reflected in the arrangement of the contents list. For storage and management purposes the digital files have bundled into compressed ZIP files. Typically the ZIP file will include multiple files or one or more folders, each containing individual files or nested sub-folders. The "download ZIP file" links in the contents list will download a ZIP file that includes all of the subordinate items in the contents list hierarchy. Contents of the ZIP file must be un-zipped before they can be viewed.
In utilizing the collection, researchers should be aware of the following details. First, there is often an overlap in the subject matter of paper and (where extant) digital files of a given series. Researchers should therefore be sure to check both formats. Secondly, the collection contains very few physical photographs as the majority of the images taken of Governor Granholm and her administration were digital. These images are usually located in the "General Office Records" subseries (but may reside elsewhere) of the following series: Communications, Economic Recovery Office, Northern Michigan Office, the Legislative Affairs subseries of Other Executive Divisions, Office of the Lieutenant Governor, and Office of the First Gentleman.
The Jennifer Granholm papers document the activities, policies, and accomplishments of the executive branch of Michigan's state government from 2003 to 2010. The collection consists of twelve series and is primarily arranged according to office of origin. The series are: Transition 2002, Legal Division, Policy Division, Executive Office, Communications Division, Economic Recovery Office, Northern Michigan Office, Other Executive Divisions, Office of the Lieutenant Governor, Office of the First Gentleman, Archived Websites, and Memorabilia. While the collection documents the full range of Governor Granholm's activities, it is especially strong in documenting the governor's efforts in the areas of economic diversification, renewable energy, education, and Michigan's response to the 2008 financial crisis. Also of note are the documents pertaining to the Governor's Hearing on the Removal of Kwame Kilpatrick from the office of Mayor of Detroit, the Legal Division files on the state's interactions with Michigan's Native American tribes, the administration's work on behalf of the University of Michigan in the Gratz and Grutter affirmative action lawsuits, the administration's response to Proposal 2, and dossiers kept on each Michigan soldier killed in action in Iraq and Afghanistan.
Subjects:
Granholm, Jennifer.; Kilpatrick, Kwame M., 1970-; Mulhern, Daniel Granholm.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Diversification in industry--Michigan.; Financial crises--United States.; Governors--Michigan.; Michigan--Economic conditions.; Michigan. Governor (2003-2011: Granholm); Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Renewable energy sources--Michigan.; Michigan--Politics and government--2001-2010.
Genre Terms:
CD-ROMs.; Websites.
- Transition 2002
  Transition 2002 documents the Granholm administration's transition to power following the 2002 gubernatorial election and is divided into two subseries: Director's Files (Lynn Johndahl) and Staff Files. Veteran Michigan lawmaker Lynn Johndahl served as the director of transition for the Granholm administration from November of 2002 through January of 2003. The Director's Files consist of the contents of binders related to the 2002 transition from the Engler administration to the Granholm administration. The Staff Files document the governor's inaugurations and plans regarding the staffing and organizational structure of the Office of the Governor. As a whole, this series provides a comprehensive yet succinct introduction to the Granholm administration's organizational structure.
  - Director’s Files (Lynn Johndahl)
    - Transition Books
      - General Descriptions of Offices and Departments circa 2003 (Box 1)
      - Department of Agriculture 2002 (Box 1)
      - Department of Career Development 2003 (Box 1)
      - Department of Civil Rights 2002 (Box 1)
      - Department of Civil Service 2002 (Box 1)
      - Department of Community Health 2002 (Box 1)
      - Consumer Industry and Services 2002 (Box 1)
      - Department of Corrections 2002 (Box 1)
      - Department of Environmental Quality 2002 (Box 1)
      - Family Independence Agency 2002 (Box 1)
      - Office of the Great Lakes 2002 (Box 1)
      - Department of History, Arts, and Libraries 2003 (Box 1)
      - Department of Infrastructure Services 2002 (Box 1)
      - Department of Information Technology 2002 (Box 1)
      - Management and Budget 2002 (Box 1)
      - Michigan Economic Development Corporation 2002 (Box 1)
      - Department of Military and Veterans Affairs 2002 (Box 1)
      - Department of Natural Resources 2002 (Box 1)
      - Office of Services to the Aging 2002 (Box 1)
      - Office of the State Budget 2002 (Box 1)
      - Office of the State Employer 2002 (Box 1)
      - Michigan State Police 2002 (Box 1)
      - Department of Transportation 2002 (Box 1)
      - Department of Treasury 2002, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Staff Files
      - Managing Transitions 2003 (Box 1)
      - Inauguration 2003, 2007 (Box 1)
      - Organizing and Staffing the Governor’s Office 2002 (Box 1)
      - First Meeting with Governor’s Cabinet 2003 (Box 1)
      - Current Structure of the Office of the Governor 2002 (Box 1)
      - Confidential Status Report Regarding State Fiscal Issues 2002 (Box 1)
      - Attorney-Client Legal Memoranda Regarding Inaugural Issues 2002 (Box 1)
      - Operational and Performance Analysis of the City of Jersey City 2001 (Box 1)
- Legal Division
  RESTRICTED until January 1, 2018
  The Legal Division series is the largest of the twelve series in the collection and contains material on a wide range of issues. The mission of the Governor's Legal Division was primarily to provide sound legal advice and act as a liaison with the Attorney General. The files contain research materials, printed email correspondence, and legal documents. The series is comprised of eleven subseries organized by staff member and a General Office Records subseries organized by topic. The staff member subseries are: Kelly Keenan: Legal Counsel, 2003-2008; Steven C. Liedel: Deputy Legal Counsel (2003-2008) and Legal Counsel (2008-2010); Don Allen: Attorney General's Office and Deputy Legal Counsel; Suzanne Sonneborn: Deputy Legal Counsel; Victoria Manning: Paralegal; Danielle M. Brown: Staff; Corina Peña Andorfer: Deputy Legal Counsel; Michelle Rick: Deputy Legal Counsel; Brandon Hofmeister: Deputy Legal Counsel; Teresa Bingman: Deputy Legal Counsel; and John Wernet: Deputy Legal Counsel.
  Kelly Keenan served as the governor's legal counsel from 2003 to 2008. The Kelly Keenan: Legal Counsel, 2003-2008 subseries documents the full range of the Legal Division's activity. Keenan's files also document the Granholm administration's preparation of an amicus curiae brief in support of the University of Michigan in the Graetz and Grutter lawsuits and contain a significant collection of materials related to the Kwame Kilpatrick removal hearing. Steven C. Liedel, served as a Deputy Legal Counsel from 2003 to 2008 and was named Legal Counsel in 2008 upon the retirement of Kelly Keenan. His records primarily document transition and legislative issues. There is also some material related to the Kwame Kilpatrick removal hearing in the Liedel subseries. Additionally, the Liedel subseries contains files for each of Governor Granholm's executive orders, directives, and proclamations. Combined, the Keenan and Liedel subseries document the full range of the department's activity, although more detailed information on a particular topic can often be found in the files of a staffer who specialized in that area.
  The other nine staffers worked in more circumscribed areas including renewable energy, economic development, corrections, tribal issues, civil rights, and education. Of particular note are Deputy Legal Counsel Michelle Rick's files documenting the administration's response to Proposal 2 and John Wernet's extensive files on Tribal Issues. The final subseries, General Office Records, documents the same topics as the paper files, but is significantly more robust in documenting legislative activity.
  - Kelly Keenan: Legal Counsel 2003-2008
    - Advisory Commission, Land Use Reform Commission 2003-2004 (Box 2)
      (earlier material from 1988 and 1998)
    - Agriculture
      - CAFTA Agreements (Central American Free Trade Agreement)/Sugar Industry 2004 (Box 2)
        [Restricted until Jan. 1, 2018 ]
      - Instant Horse Racing 2008 (Box 2)
      - Instant Racing 2007 (Box 2)
      - Item Pricing 2004-2006 (Box 2)
      - Racing Commission 2002-2003 (Box 2)
      - State Fair 2003-2004 (Box 2)
    - Appointments
      - Appointments to State Boards and Commissions by the Legislature 2003 (Box 2)
      - Board of State Canvassers/Jones, Dorothy (Dotty) 2002, 2004 (Box 2)
      - Certificate of Needs Commission 2003 (Box 2)
      - Chief Compliance Officer 2005-2009 (Box 2)
      - Eastern Michigan University Board of Regents 2006 (Box 2)
      - Environmental Policy Advisor 2003 (Box 2)
      - Family Independence Agency 2003 (Box 2)
      - Mackinac Island State Park Commission 2003 (Box 2)
      - Michigan Commission on Aging 2003 (Box 2)
      - Michigan Economic Growth Authority (MEGA) 2003 (Box 2)
      - Michigan Gaming Control Board 2006-2007 (Box 2)
      - Parole Board 2003, 2006 (Box 2)
      - Senate Appointments Questionnaire 2002 (Box 2)
      - Smart Growth Commission 2003 (Box 2)
      - State Boundary Commission 2005 (Box 2)
      - State Police 2003-2006 (Box 2)
      - Surgeon General 2002 (Box 2)
      - State Treasurer 2003-2006 (Box 2)
      - Utility Consumer Participation Board 2003-2004 (Box 2)
      - Wayne County Airport Authority Board 2007 (Box 2)
      - White House Conference on Aging 2004 (Box 2)
      - Workers Compensation Board of Magistrates 2003-2005 (Box 2)
    - Attorney General
      - American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) Complaint/Indigent Defense 2007 (Box 2)
      - General/AG Advice-Potential State Shutdown 2007 (Box 2)
      - Amicus Recommendations 2006-2007 (Box 2)
      - Attorney General 2003 (Box 2)
        (includes correspondence regarding various court cases, and phone lists)
      - Attorney General -- Department of Information Technology (DIT) Memorandum of Understanding 2004-2005 (Box 2)
      - Attorney Grievance Commission/Falk Grievance 2003 (Box 2)
      - Becker v Granholm (Education Scholarship) 2003 (Box 2)
      - Brockman, David/Litigation Against Eli Lilly Company 2007 (Box 2)
      - City of Lansing vs. State of Michigan and Wolverine Pipeline Company 2005 (Box 2)
      - County Road Association of Michigan Case/Motor Vehicle Sales Tax 2004 (Box 2)
      - DaimlerChrysler 2003 (Box 2)
      - Executive Reorganization Orders/Advice and Counsel
        - Abolishing Department of History, Arts, and Libraries 2007 (Box 2)
        - Abolishing Michigan Broadband Development Authority 2007 (Box 2)
        - Career and Technical Education Responsibilities 2007 (Box 2)
        - Consolidation of Human Resources Operations 2007 (Box 2)
        - Consolidation of Internal Audit Functions 2007 (Box 2)
        - Consolidation of Public Finance Authority Administration 2007 (Box 2)
        - Consolidation of Public School Academy Oversight 2007 (Box 2)
        - Consolidation of State Accounting Functions 2007 (Box 2)
        - Consolidation of State Property Disposal Functions 2007 (Box 2)
        - Creation of Office of Health Services Inspector General 2007 (Box 2)
        - Transfer of Civil Service Commission 2007 (Box 2)
        - Transfer of Department of Information Technology 2007 (Box 2)
      - Fieger/Cox Matter 2005-2007 (Box 2)
      - Governor Opinion Request/Removal From Office 2003 (Box 2)
      - Grievance Filed by David Roberts Against Cox and Alan Wilk 2004 (Box 2)
      - Item Pricing/Wal-Mart Settlement 2006 (Box 2)
      - Letter to Departments Regarding Legal Advisor 2004 (Box 3)
      - Letter to Departments Reinstituting Survey Process Regarding Legal Services 2004 (Box 3)
      - Litigation
        - 2004 (Box 3)
        - 2005 (Box 3)
        - 2006 (Box 3)
        - 2007 (Box 3)
        - 2008 (Box 3)
      - National Pride at Work vs. Granholm (Marriage Amendment) 2005 (Box 3)
      - Opinion Request
        - Five-Day Period 2007 (Box 3)
        - Intermediate School District (ISD) 2003 (Box 3)
        - SB 1602 2004 (Box 3)
      - Opinions 2003 (Box 3)
      - Political Activities, William J. Richards Memo 2001 (Box 3)
      - Preliminary Examinations 2005-2006 (Box 3)
      - Project Joshua/Wayne County 2004-2006 (Box 3)
      - Public Service Commission 2004 (Box 3)
      - Removal of Local Officials 2003 (Box 3)
      - Request for Advice and Counsel Regarding Draft Proposed Executive Reorganization Orders, (Governor Letters to AG Regarding Representation 2007 (Box 3)
      - Settlements Over $200,000 2002-2003 (Box 3)
      - Special Assistant Attorney General (SAAG) 2003 (Box 3)
      - Spending Analysis Report 2004 (Box 3)
      - Stetzer v Attorney General 2003 (Box 3)
      - Teeter/Scott 2003-2004 (Box 3)
      - Thom, Kevin 2004 (Box 3)
    - Auditor General
      - Annual Report 2002-2003, 2006 (Box 3)
      - Auditor General Office 2007-2008 (Box 3)
        (photocopies from 1996)
      - Auditor General Reports 2006 (Box 3)
      - Duties of Auditor 2003 (Box 3)
      - Employee Safety and Health Programs 2003 (Box 3)
      - Forensic Science Division/State Police 2003 (Box 3)
      - General Framework 2003 (Box 3)
      - Natural Resources, Real Estate Acquisition and Disposition 2003 (Box 3)
      - Office of Racing Commissioner Audit Report 2003 (Box 3)
    - Budget
      - Detroit Police Officers Association (DPOA) circa 2005 (Box 4)
      - Job Growth 2003 (Box 4)
      - Revenue Sharing 2005 (Box 4)
      - Taxpayer Bill of Rights (TABOR) 2005 (Box 4)
      - Venture Capital Overview 2004 (Box 4)
    - Civil Rights
      - Amicus Brief Filed by Attorney General/Garg v. Macomb County Community Health Services 2004 (Box 4)
      - Ann Arbor Film Festival Matter/ACLU 2006-2007 (Box 4)
      - BAMN-Proposal 2 Lawsuit 2006-2007 (Box 4)
      - Civil Rights 2003-2004 (earlier photocopies dating to 1970s) (Box 4)
      - Communities for Equity v. Michigan High School Athletic Association (MHSAA) /Female Athletes 2004 (Box 4)
      - Michigan Civil Rights Initiative/By Any Means Necessary (BAMN) 2005-2006, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Proposal 2/Equality/Promoting Diversity 2006 (Box 4)
      - Women’s Commission/Connerly Initiative (Drulet) 2005 (Box 4)
    - Civil Service
      - Authorized Payroll Deductions of Employee Contributions to Union-Sponsored Political Action Committees (PACS) 2006 (Box 4)
      - Civil Service Commission 2007 (Box 4)
      - Civil Service Rules 2003-2007 (photocopies from 1976) (Box 4)
      - Civil Service Rules, Temporary Layoff During Fiscal Emergency 2007 (Box 4)
      - Executive Directive 2003-24 2003-2004 (Box 4)
      - Human Resources Study 2003-2006 (Box 4)
      - Personnel Issues 2003 (Box 4)
      - State Officers’ Compensation Commission (SOCC) 2004 (Box 4)
    - Community Health
      - Abortion 2001-2006 (photocopies from 1998) (Box 4)
      - Adult Foster Care 2005-2006 (Box 4)
      - Canadian Prescription Drugs 2003 (Box 4)
      - Community Health Certificate of Need (CON) 2002-2008 (Box 4)
      - Community Health 2005-2007 (Box 4)
      - Detroit Health Care Stabilization Group 2003 (Box 5)